A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Special Collections, Grant Funded Materials FA1839
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Special Collections, Grant Funded Materials
1951-2018
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1839
27.63 Cubic Feet 71 containers
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of grant funded materials, including reports, correspondence, and publications, created by Ford Foundation grantees as part of, or in addition to, the agreed terms of their Ford Foundation grants. These materials span from the 1950s to the 2010s. Sometimes these files are referred to as "grant attachments." These materials are considered separate from the Ford Foundation historical grant files which contain organizational information, grant proposals, reports, documents outlining the terms of the grant, budgetary information, and signed grant agreement letters. Many of the grant-funded materials in this collection came to the Rockefeller Archive Center as part of a grant room clean-up project. Some files in the collection are annex and appendix materials that have been separated from a larger report. A small portion of the documents within folders are labelled numerically. Contextual information regarding the Ford Foundation grant under which the materials were created, including the name of the grantee, the dates of the grant, the grant number (ex: PA 09800953 or (06700190)), the grant purpose statement, the grant amount, and names of Ford Foundation program officers responsible for the grant have been added to the description field when they are identifiable.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged in 8 series:
1. Readers International Books (08450773), 1981-1990
2. Educational Facilities Laboratories (05800096), 1959-1973
3. Publications and Radio Reports, 1951-1953
4. Reports from the Philippines and Thailand, 1971-1977
5. Grant File Attachments - Publications and Reports, 1955-2018
6. Gender, Racial, and Ethnic Justice (GREJ) - Reports and Publications, 2009-2018
7. A Study of the Performing Arts (Symphony, Opera, Ballet, Theatre) Prepared for Ford Foundation December 1971, Eric Marder Associates, Inc., 1971-1972
8. Peace and Social Justice (PSJ), Governance and Civil Society (GCS) - Publications from Grantees and Researchers, 1997-2018
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Rockefeller Archive Center received seven accessions containing Grant Funded Materials from the Ford Foundation between 2019 and 2021 - Accessions 2020:012, 2019:055, 2019:097, 2019:118, 2019:088, 2020:032, 2021:010.
- Readers International Books (08450773), 1981-1990; 1; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Grantee: Readers International, Inc.
  Grant Dates: 1984 September 01-1987 June 30
  Grant Number: 08450773
  Grant Purpose:"Partial support for a series of books of human rights significance by Third World or East European authors"
  Grant Amount: $140,000.00; $140,000.00
  Ford Program Officer(s): Marks, Stephen P.
  - Rue du Retour by Abdellatif Laabi, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hajji Musa and the Hindu Fire-Walker by Ahmed Essop, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Homage to the Eighth District: Tales from Budapest by Giorgio and Nicola Pressburger, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Queue by Vladimir Sorokin, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blues for a Lost Childhood by Antonio Torres, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - A Ride on the Whirlwind by Sipho Sepamla, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - A Cadre School Life, Six Chapters by Yang Jiang, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The House of Twilight by Yun Heung-gil, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Winter Quarters by Osvaldo Soriano, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - El Infierno by Carlos Martinez Moreno, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Edge of the World by Janusz Anderman, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Triste's History by Horacio Vazquez Rial, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - My Childhood at the Gate of Unrest by Paul Goma, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Educational Facilities Laboratories (05800096), 1959-1973; 2; 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  Biographical / Historical
  The Educational Facilities Laboratories (EFL) was an independent nonprofit research organization established by the Ford Foundation in 1958 with an appropriation of $4.5 million. The organization's goal was to help American schools and colleges improve their facilities through research and experimentation.
  Over its 28-year existence, EFL spurred innovation in school architecture by sponsoring research projects and programs, holding conferences, and awarding grants to thousands of school districts, colleges, and nonprofit organizations throughout the United States and Canada. Committed to spreading the word of such advancement, EFL distributed more than two million copies of its publications on research, experimentation, and emerging trends.
  Grantee: Educational Facilities Laboratories, Inc.
  Grant Dates: 1958 February 19-1979 December 31
  Grant Number: 05800096
  Grant Purpose: General support
  Grant Amount: $25,500,000.00; $25,500,000.00
  Ford Program Officer(s): Lynch, Barbara D.; Meade, Edward J.
  - The Cost of a Schoolhouse: A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Relocatable School Facilities by Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Guide to Alternatives for Financing School Buildings: A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - New Schools for a New Education: A Report from Ann Arbor, Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - School Construction Systems Development: The Project and the Schools, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - College Students Live Here, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Planning for Schools with Television: Design for ETV, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Joint Occupancy: Profiles of Significant Schools, Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The Schools and Urban Renewal: A Case Study from New Haven by Terry Ferrer, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Bricks and Mortarboards: A Report On College Planning and Building, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Middle Schools: Profiles of Significant Schools by Judith Murphy, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Schools for Early Childhood by Paul Abramson, Profiles of Significant Schools, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1970 September (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Schools Without Walls: Profiles of Significant Schools, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - New Building on Campus: Six Designs for a College Communications Center, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Conventional Gymnasium vs. Geodesic Field House: A Comparative Study of High School Physical Education and Assembly Facilities, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Case Studies of Educational Facilities #6, A College Health Center by Bernard Bard, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - New Campuses for Old: A Case Study of Four Colleges that Moved by S.B. Zisman and Catherine Powell, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - To Build or Not to Build: A Report on the Utilization and Planning of Instructional Facilities in Small Colleges, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Air Structures for School Sports by Nan Robertson, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Divisible Auditoriums, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1966 May (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - High Schools 1962: Profiles of Significant Schools: A Status Report on Educational Change and Architectural Consequence, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Educational Change and Architectural Consequences by Ronald Gross and Judith Murphy, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Experiment in Planning an Urban High School: The Baltimore Charette by Sherwood D. Kohn, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1969 November (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Schools Scheduling by Computer: The Story of GASP by Judith Murphy and Robert Sutter, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - The School Library: Facilities for Independent Study in the Secondary School by Ralph Ellsworth and Hobart D. Wagener, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Transformation of the Schoolhouse, 1969 Annual Report, Educational Facilities Laboratories (EFL) (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Profiles of Significant Schools: On the Way to Work: 5 Vocationally-Oriented Schools, Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Ring the Alarm! A Memo to the Schools on Fire and Human Beings: Some Suggestions for Principals and Other School Officials on the Management of People to Meet the Emergency of School Fires, Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1959 December (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Education and World Affairs Report on Programs, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - The Place of the Arts in New Towns, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - The Early Learning Center: Profiles of Significant Schools, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories by Sherwood Kohn, 1970 January (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Contrast Rendition in School Lighting by Foster K. Sampson, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1970 January (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - A College in the City: An Alternative, A Report from Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - The New Campus in Britain: Ideas of Consequence for the United States by Richard P. Dober, Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1965 July (Box 5, Folder 47)
- Publications and Radio Reports, 1951-1953; 3; 0.85 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box and 1 legal box
  - The Jeffersonian Heritage, edited by Dumas Malone, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - American Heritage Project of the American Library Association, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Great Men and Great Issues in Our American Heritage, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Scripts from "The People Act," a Series of 26 Radio Programs, 1952 January-June (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Radio Reports, Texts of Broadcasts, Created for the Ford Foundation, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Grants to the Fund for Adult Education/Other Ford Foundation Grants Information Sheets, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 53)
- Reports from the Philippines and Thailand, 1971-1977; 4; 0.94 Cubic Feet 2 legal document boxes
  - Terminal Report, Warren R. Phillipson, Graduate Assistant in Soil Science, Ford Foundation-Sponsored U.P.-Cornell Graduate Education Program, U.P. College of Agriculture, Los Banos, Philippines, 1972 June (Box 6, Folder 54)
    Grantee: Cornell University
    Grant Dates: 1965 April 16-1970 September 07
    Grant Number: 06500153
    Grant Purpose: Participation in the program to strengthen the University of the Philippines College of Agriculture
    Grant Amount: $2,090,750.00; $2,090,750.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Havener, Robert D.; Simmons, Ozzie G.
  - Resettlement Ecology: Research Design for the Study of the Social and Environmental Impact of Agricultural Settlement Projects in Southeast Asian Forest Areas, A. Terry Rambo, University of Malaya, 1977 August (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Analytical Report, Ford Foundation/Educational Projects, Inc., Assistance to Mindanao State University (1965-1971), Prepared by Educational Projects, Inc., 1971 June (Box 6, Folder 56-57)
    Grantee: Educational Projects, Incorporated
    Grant Dates: 1967 July 19-1969 July 18
    Grant Number: 06700433
    Grant Purpose: Support of southeast asian participants in the International Conference on Southeast Asian Studies at Kota Kinabalu, Sabah, November 1977
    Grant Amount: $394,000.00; $394,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Assistance to Mindanao State University in the Philippines
  - Terminal Report, Roger D. Dutcher, Graduate Assistant in Agronomy (Fruit Crops), Ford Foundation-Sponsored U.P.-Cornell Graduate Education Program, U.P. College of Agriculture, Los Banos, Philippines, 1971 April (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Terminal Report, Robert J. Grant, Graduate Assistant in Animal Husbandry, Ford Foundation-Sponsored U.P.-Cornell Graduate Education Program, U.P. College of Agriculture, Los Banos, Philippines, 1972 May (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Terminal Report, Alan C. Early, Graduate Assistant in Agricultural Engineering, Ford Foundation-Sponsored U.P.-Cornell Graduate Education Program, U.P. College of Agriculture, Los Banos, Philippines, 1972 March (Box 6, Folder 60)
    Conditions Governing Access
  - Terminal Report, Malcolm C. Bourne, Visiting Professor of Agricultural Chemistry (Food Science) Ford Foundation-Sponsored U.P.-Cornell Graduate Education Program, U.P. College of Agriculture, Los Banos, Philippines, 1971 March (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Terminal Report, Otto E. Schultz, Visiting Professor of Plant Pathology, Ford Foundation-Sponsored U.P.-Cornell Graduate Education Program, U.P. College of Agriculture, Los Banos, Philippines, 1971 May (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Ford Foundation Grants to Mindanao State University: A Narrative Report (1965-1971), Marawi City, Philippines, Volume 1, 1972 May (Box 7, Folder 63)
    Grantee: Mindanao State University
    Grant Dates: 1969 July 01-1973 December 31
    Grant Number: 06900436
    Grant Purpose: Assistance to the university
    Grant Amount: $245,520.00; $237,292.60
    Ford Program Officer(s): Bunker, Samuel E.; Frodin, Reuben
  - Methods of Family Planning, Book 1: Introduction to the Methods, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Methods of Family Planning, Book 4: Summary, undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Equality of Educational Opportunity: A Study of Primary Schooling in Thailand, William P. Fuller, 1974 April (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - The Rate of Return to Investment in Education in Thailand by Mark Blaug, A Report to the National Education Council on the Third Educational Development Plan, Bangkok, 1971 December (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Report on the Ford Foundation Grant 700-0095 to Silliman University, Covering the Period July 1, 1969 to June 30, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    Grantee: Silliman University
    Grant Dates: 1969 December 09-1974 March 28
    Grant Number: 07000095
    Grant Purpose: Development of undergraduate program
    Grant Amount: $190,000.00; $190,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Frodin, Reuben; Simmons, Ozzie G.
  - Terminal Report on the Ford Foundation Grant 700-0095A (July 1, 1972-June 30, 1974) to Silliman University, Dumaguete City, Philippines, 1974 September 5 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Narrative Report on Ford Foundation Grant Number 690-0436 to the Mindanao State University, July 1, 1969-June 30, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 70)
- Grant File Attachments - Publications and Reports, 1955-2018; 5; 23.46 Cubic Feet
  - PA#8900052 - Tumbas Anonimas: Informe Sobre la Identificacion de Restos de Victimas de La Represion Ilegal, Equipo Argentino de Anthropologia Forense, Mauricio Cohen Salama, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    Grantee: Argentine Group of Forensic Anthropologists
    Grant Dates: 1988 October 01-1992 June 30
    Grant Number: 08900052
    Grant Purpose: Support for scientific work to identify the "disappeared" in Argentina
    Grant Amount: $115,000.00; $115,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Shifter, Michael E.
  - PA#8800784 - El Impacto de la Reforma en Ciudades Intermedias y Pequenas de Colombia, Pedro Santana Rodriguez, 1991 August (Box 8, Folder 72)
    Grantee: National Forum for Colombia Foundation (Foro)
    Grant Dates: 1988 May 01-1991 December 31
    Grant Number: 08800784
    Grant Purpose: Policy research and outreach on municipal reform and urban services for the poor in Colombia
    Grant Amount: $98,000.00; $97,061.90
    Ford Program Officer(s): Offenheiser, Jr., Raymond C.
  - PA#8800784 - Investigacion Accion Participativa en Colombia, O. Fals, L. Zamosc, P. Santana, F. Velasquez, J. Cardenas, C. Garcia (ed.), Punta de Lanza, Foro Nacional Por Colombia, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - PA#8800296 - Saving Public Housing from Demolition or Sale: A Description of Relevant Laws, National Housing Law Project, 1988 October (Box 8, Folder 74)
    Grantee: National Housing Law Project
    Grant Dates: 08800296
    Grant Number: $112,000.00; $112,000.00
    Grant Purpose: Support to compile a series of case studies documenting public housing projects experiencing abandonment and demolition of units
    Grant Amount: $112,000.00; $112,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Andrews, Nancy O.
  - PA#8701084 - One-Third of a Nation: A Report of the Commission on Minority Participation in Education and American Life, American Council on Education and Education Commission of the States, 1988 May (Box 8, Folder 75)
    Grantee: American Council on Education (ACE)
    Grant Dates: 1987 October 01-1988 December 31
    Grant Number: 08701084
    Grant Purpose: Partial support for an initiative to enhance the role and participation of minorities in higher education
    Grant Amount: $100,000.00; $100,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Bernstein, Alison R.
  - PA#86550 - Images of Mexico in the United States, edited by John H. Coatsworth and Carlos Rico, papers prepared for the Bilateral Commission on the Future of United States-Mexican Relations, Center for U.S.-Mexican Relations, University of California, San Diego, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - PA#871084 - Minorities on Campus: A Handbook for Enhancing Diversity, American Council on Education, Washington, D.C., 1989 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    Ford Program Officer(s): 1987 October 01-1988 December 31
  - PA#8850503 - Problematica de la Mujer Peruana en el Campo Laboral by Rosario Gomez G. and Karen Weinberger V., Universidad Del Pacifico, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    Grantee: Universidad Del Pacifico
    Grant Dates: 1988 March 01-1992 March 31
    Grant Number: 08850503
    Grant Purpose: Support to develop and test teaching materials on women's economic activities
    Grant Amount: $19,500.00; $19,500.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Anderson, Jeanine; Vallenas, Sandra
  - PA#89782 - Women and Politics Worldwide edited by Barbara J. Nelson and Najma Chowdhury, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    Grantee: University of Minnesota Foundation
    Grant Dates: 1989 July 01-1993 June 30
    Grant Number: 08900782
    Grant Purpose: Support for research and production of a book entitled "Women and Politics Worldwide"
    Grant Amount: $186,000.00; $186,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Heisler, Michele; Zeitlin, June H.; Huntley, Lynn
  - PA#8851086 - Justicia Militar en Chile, Colegio de Abogados, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    Grantee: Chilean Bar Association
    Grant Dates: 1988 September 15-1989 August 21
    Grant Number: 08851086
    Grant Purpose: Support for research on military justice in Chile
    Grant Amount: $15,000.00; $12,684.74
  - PA#7800169 - Coming of Age in the Ghetto: A Dilemma of Youth Unemployment by Garth L. Mangum and Stephen F. Seninger, A Report to the Ford Foundation - Policy Studies in Employment and Welfare Number 33, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    Grantee: George Washington University
    Grant Dates: 1978 February 01-1981 January 31
    Grant Number: 07800169
    Grant Purpose: Part. Suppt. For the family impact seminar to test the substantiveadmin./political feasibliity/desirability of family impact analysi
    Grant Amount: $75,000.00; $75,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Lisniewski, Theresa H.; Saario, Terry
  - PA#8950538 - El Pan Nuestro by Manuel Lajo, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    Grantee: Center for A New Economy and Society
    Grant Dates: 1989 April 01-1990 July 01
    Grant Number: 08950538
    Grant Purpose: Research to develop a new food subsidy policy for Peru's urban poor
    Grant Amount: $25,000.00; $25,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Cartier, William J.
  - PA#8690550 - Foreign Policy in US-Mexican Relations edited by Rosario Green and Peter H. Smith, Volume 5, Center for U.S.-Mexican Relations, University of California, San Diego, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    Grantee: Foundation-Administered Project (FAP)
    Grant Dates: 1986 June 01-1993 October 31
    Grant Number: 08690550
    Grant Purpose: Support For The Organization And Activities Of A Commission On U.S.-Mexican Relations
    Grant Amount: $2,000,000.00; $2,000,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Cox, Stephen B.; Heginbotham, Stanley J. (Stanely Jay); Collins, Norman R.
  - PA#8600509 - The Economic Future of American Families: Income and Wealth Trends by Frank Levy and Richard C. Michel, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    Grantee: The Urban Institute
    Grant Dates: 1986 June 01-1989 July 15
    Grant Number: 08600509
    Grant Purpose: Study of economic growth, standards of living, income inequality and related social welfare needs and responses (welfare state)
    Grant Amount: $176,500.00; $176,500.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Lanigan, John; O'Connor, Alice
  - PA#8700104 - Handsome Dividends: A Handbook to Demystify the U.S. Hispanic Markets published by the Hispanic Policy Development Project, New York, NY and Washington, D.C., 1994 (Box 10, Folder 85)
    Grantee: Hispanic Policy Development Project, Inc.
    Grant Dates: 1986 October 01-1994 June 30
    Grant Number: 08700104
    Grant Purpose: General support for research, analysis, and dissemination activities on policies affecting young hispanics in the U.S.
    Grant Amount: $1,150,000.00; $1,150,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Romero, Anthony D.
  - PA#8650076 - I Seminario de Investigaciones Sociales en la Amazonia, National Council of Science and Technology, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    Grantee: National Council of Science and Technology (Concytec)
    Grant Dates: 1985 November 01-1987 May 31
    Grant Number: 08650076
    Grant Purpose: Support for a national congress of anthropology (Peru)
    Grant Amount: $9,000.00; $9,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Anderson, Jeanine
  - PA#8950599 - Politicas Sociales, Mujeres y Gobierno Local edited by Dagmar Raczynski and Claudio Serrano, Corporation for Latin American Economic Research, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 87)
    Grantee: Corporation for Latin American Economic Research (CIEPLAN)
    Grant Dates: 1989 May 01-1992 June 30
    Grant Number: 08950599
    Grant Purpose: A subregional working group on local government, women and social policy (Latin America)
    Grant Amount: $40,000.00; $40,000.00
    Ford Program Officer(s): Vallenas, Sandra
  - PA#8750398 - La Situacion Poblacionel Peruana, Balance y Perspectivas published by Alberto Varillas Montenegro and Patricia Mostajo de Muente, Andean Institute for Population Studies and Development, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    Grantee: Andean Institute for Population Studies and Development (Inandep)